<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20130925</CreaDate><CreaTime>13111300</CreaTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><ModDate>20170202</ModDate><ModTime>154606</ModTime><scaleRange><minScale>150000000</minScale><maxScale>5000</maxScale></scaleRange><ArcGISProfile>ItemDescription</ArcGISProfile></Esri><toolbox name="ERG Tools" alias="erg"><arcToolboxHelpPath>c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.3\Help\gp</arcToolboxHelpPath><toolsets/></toolbox><dataIdInfo><idCitation><resTitle>ERG Tools</resTitle></idCitation><idPurp>These tools implement the 2016 Emergency Response Guidebook, allowing the spill material to be entered either by the name of the chemical, or by the Placard ID.

The 2016 Emergency Response Guidebook (ERG2016) was developed jointly by Transport Canada (TC), the U.S. Department of Transportation (DOT), the Secretariat of Transport and Communications of Mexico (SCT) and with the collaboration of CIQUIME (Centro de Información Química para Emergencias) of Argentina, for use by fire fighters, police, and other emergency services personnel who may be the first to arrive at the scene of a transportation incident involving dangerous goods. It is primarily a guide to aid first responders in quickly identifying the specific or generic hazards of the material(s) involved in the incident, and protecting themselves and the general public during the initial response phase of the incident.</idPurp><searchKeys><keyword>ERG</keyword><keyword>Emergency Response Guidebook</keyword><keyword>ERG2016</keyword></searchKeys><idAbs>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Two tools that enable the implementation of the 2016 Emergency Response Guidebook, for when an emergency responder encounters a spill of a hazardous substance. By entering either the name of the hazardous substance, or a Placard ID, along with a number of other parameters that define the size of the spill, the time of day and the wind direction, the areas of Initial Isolation and Protective Action can be calculated and displayed.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</idAbs></dataIdInfo><distInfo><distributor><distorFormat><formatName>ArcToolbox Toolbox</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv></metadata>
