<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20130415</CreaDate><CreaTime>09543300</CreaTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><ModDate>20130718</ModDate><ModTime>175831</ModTime><scaleRange><minScale>150000000</minScale><maxScale>5000</maxScale></scaleRange><ArcGISProfile>ItemDescription</ArcGISProfile></Esri><dataIdInfo><idCitation><resTitle>Multidimensional Zonal Statistics</resTitle></idCitation><searchKeys><keyword>zonal</keyword><keyword>statistic</keyword><keyword>variable</keyword><keyword>netcdf</keyword></searchKeys><idAbs>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Calculates zonal statistics for a selected variable over the non-surface dimensions of a multidimensional dataset, such as netCDF, HDF, or other dataset accessible through the OPeNDAP protocol.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</idAbs><resConst><Consts><useLimit>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;ArcGIS for Desktop Basic: Requires Spatial Analyst&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;ArcGIS for Desktop Standard: Requires Spatial Analyst&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;ArcGIS for Desktop Advanced: Requires Spatial Analyst&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</useLimit></Consts></resConst></dataIdInfo><distInfo><distributor><distorFormat><formatName>ArcToolbox Tool</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><tool name="MultidimensionalZonalStatistics" displayname="Multidimensional Zonal Statistics" toolboxalias="mds" xmlns=""><parameters><param name="in_zone_data" displayname="Input Raster or Feature Zone Data" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="Raster Layer or Feature Layer" expression="in_zone_data"><dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Dataset that defines the zones. The zones can be defined by an integer raster or a feature layer.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference><pythonReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Dataset that defines the zones. The zones can be defined by an integer raster or a feature layer.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</pythonReference></param><param name="in_value_file" displayname="Input Value File or URL String" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="File or String" expression="in_value_file"><dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 0 4;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The path to a multidimensional dataset on disk or a URL that references a dataset located on an OPeNDAP server. This dataset provides values over which the zonal statistic will be performed.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference><pythonReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 0 4;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The path to a multidimensional dataset on disk or a URL that references a dataset located on an OPeNDAP server. This dataset provides values over which the zonal statistic will be performed.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</pythonReference></param><param name="variable" displayname="Variable" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="String" expression="variable"><dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The variable of the multidimensional dataset for which to calculate the zonal statistic.  Variables that are regularly gridded or follow the discrete sampling geometry conventions outlined in the Tool Usage are supported.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference><pythonReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The variable of the multidimensional dataset for which to calculate the zonal statistic.  Variables that are regularly gridded or follow the discrete sampling geometry conventions outlined in the Tool Usage are supported.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</pythonReference></param><param name="out_netcdf_file" displayname="Output netCDF File" type="Required" direction="Output" datatype="File" expression="out_netcdf_file"><dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The output multidimensional zonal statistics netCDF file. NetCDF format is used because the output file will contain a variable with the same dimensionality as the input variable.  Filename should have extension .nc.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference><pythonReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The output multidimensional zonal statistics netCDF file. NetCDF format is used because the output file will contain a variable with the same dimensionality as the input variable. Filename should have extension .nc.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</pythonReference></param><param name="statistic_type" displayname="Statistic Type" type="Optional" direction="Input" datatype="String" expression="{MEAN | MAJORITY | MAXIMUM | MEDIAN | MINIMUM | MINORITY | RANGE | STD | SUM | VARIANCE | VARIETY}"><dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Statistic type to be calculated.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;UL&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;MEAN — Calculates the average of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;MAJORITY — Determines the value that occurs most often of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. Only available for variables with an integer datatype.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;MAXIMUM — Determines the largest value of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;MEDIAN — Determines the median value of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. Only available for variables with an integer datatype.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;MINIMUM — Determines the smallest value of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;MINORITY — Determines the value that occurs least often of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. Only available for variables with an integer datatype.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;RANGE — Calculates the difference between the largest and smallest value of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;STD — Calculates the standard deviation of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;SUM — Calculates the total value of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;VARIANCE — Calculates the variance of all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;VARIETY — Calculates the number of unique values for all records at each non-surface dimensional slice in the multidimensional dataset that belong to the same zone as the output record. Only available for variables with an integer datatype.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;/UL&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The statistic types MAJORITY, MEDIAN, MINORITY, and VARIETY will only operate on variables with integer datatypes. If a variable with a non-integer datatype is selected, these options will not be available.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The default statistic type is MEAN.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference><pythonReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Statistic type to be calculated. Choose from {MEAN | MAJORITY | MAXIMUM | MEDIAN | MINIMUM | MINORITY | RANGE | STD | SUM | VARIANCE | VARIETY}. The statistic types MAJORITY, MEDIAN, MINORITY, and VARIETY will only operate on variables with integer datatypes.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</pythonReference></param><param name="ignore_nodata" displayname="Ignore NoData in Calculations" type="Optional" direction="Input" datatype="Boolean" expression="{IGNORE | NO_IGNORE}"><dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Specifies how nulls and missing values will be interpreted.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;UL&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;CHECKED — for the purpose of calculating statistics, records in the 'Input File or URL String' dataset meeting one of the NoData conditions below will not be included in the calculations.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;UNCHECKED — for the purpose of calculating statistics, if any record in the 'Input File or URL String' dataset located within a given zone meets one of the NoData conditions below, all records in that zone will be treated as NoData.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;/UL&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The following variable attributes determine if a value should be considered as NoData:&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;OL&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;_FillValue — specifies the fill value used to pre-fill disk space allocated to the variable. Any value equal to the _FillValue should be considered as NoData.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;missing_value -- scalar or vector containing values indicating missing data. Any value equal to the missing_value should be considered as NoData.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;/OL&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference><pythonReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Specifies how nulls and missing values will be interpreted. Choose from {IGNORE | NO_IGNORE}. If IGNORE is chosen, for the purpose of calculating statistics, records that are NoData in the 'in_value_dataset' will not be included in the calculations. If NO_IGNORE is chosen, if any record in a given zone is NoData, all records in that zone will be treated as NoData.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</pythonReference></param><param name="zone_field" displayname="Zone Field" type="Optional" direction="Input" datatype="String" expression="{zone_field}"><dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Field that holds the values that define each zone. It can be an integer or a string field of the zone dataset.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference><pythonReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Field that holds the values that define each zone. It can be an integer or a string field of the zone dataset.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</pythonReference></param></parameters><summary>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 0 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Calculates zonal statistics for a selected variable over the non-surface dimensions of a multidimensional dataset, such as netCDF, HDF, or other dataset accessible through the OPeNDAP protocol.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</summary><usage>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;UL&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;This tool performs zonal statistics for variables in a multidimensional dataset that are either regularly gridded or follow a discrete sampling geometry. Supported discrete sampling geometries are 'point', 'timeseries', or 'profile' feature types that use orthogonal or incomplete multidimensional array data representations according with the NetCDF Climate and Forecast (CF) Metadata Conventions, version 1.6.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;A zone is defined as all areas in the input zone dataset that have the same value. The areas do not have to be contiguous. Both raster and feature datasets can be used for the zone input.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Non-surface dimensions are defined as any dimensions other than x and y (e.g. longitude and latitude) in the multidimensional dataset.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The output netCDF file will contain an output variable having the same shape, name, and attributes as the input variable. Its values, however, will be the result of applying the zonal statistic.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The zonal statistic is applied over the non-surface dimensions of the multidimensional dataset. As examples, for a regularly gridded variable in dimensions x, y, z, t (where x and y are surface dimensions), this tool will calculate x-y zonal statistics for each (z, t) slice. Likewise, a discrete geometry variable indexed by (station, t) with corresponding surface dimensions x(station) and y(station) will have (x, y) zonal statistics calculated for each t-slice. In this case, the value of the variable at each station within a zone will be given the statistical value of the zone.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;For regularly gridded variables, it is recommended that the input zone dataset be a raster. For discrete geometry variables, it is recommended that the input zone dataset be a polygon ShapeFile. If the input zone dataset is not the recommended type, it will be converted to the recommended type.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;For regularly gridded variables, when the input zone dataset is a raster dataset with the same resolution, they will be matched directly. If the resolutions are different, an internal resampling is applied to make them match before the zonal operations are performed. Should there be any NoData cells in the input zone dataset, the resampling may cause there to be larger areas of NoData in your output than you might expect. To avoid this situation, Resample the input zone dataset to match the resolution of the regularly gridded variable. To ensure that the results of the conversion will align properly with the regularly gridded variable, it is recommend that you 'Make NetCDF Raster Layer' from the variable and then check that the extent and snap raster are set appropriately in the environment settings and the raster settings.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;For regularly gridded variables, if the input zone dataset is a point feature dataset, it is possible to have more than one point contained within any particular cell of the value input raster. For such cells, the zone value is determined by the point with the highest feature ID.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;For regularly gridded variables, if the input zone dataset has overlapping polygons, the zonal analysis will not be performed for each individual polygon. Since the feature input is converted to a raster, each location can only have one value. However, for discrete geometry variables, if the input zone dataset has overlapping polygons, the zonal analysis will be performed for each individual polygon, but the value of the variable in overlapping zones will be equal to the statistical quantity calculated for the last zone read. The order the zones are read is arbitrary.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The statistic types MAJORITY, MINORITY, MEDIAN, and VARIETY will only operate on variables with an integer data type.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;For the MAJORITY and MINORITY statistic types, when there is a tie the output statistic is the lowest of the tied values.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;LI&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The default statistic type is MEAN.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/LI&gt;&lt;/UL&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</usage><scriptExamples><scriptExample><title>MultidimensionalZonalStatistics example 1 (Python window)</title><para>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;This example determines for each zone the mean value in each non-surface dimensional slice of the variable 'temperature' in the netCDF file 'netcdf.nc'.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</para><code>import arcpy

arcpy.MultidimensionalZonalStatistics_mds("zones", "c:/data/netcdf.nc", \
    "temperature", "c:/data/zonal_netcdf.nc", "MEAN", "IGNORE", "Value")</code></scriptExample></scriptExamples><scriptExamples><scriptExample><title>MultidimensionalZonalStatistics example 2 (stand-alone script)</title><para>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;This example determines for each zone the mean value in each non-surface dimensional slice of the variable 'temperature' in the netCDF file 'netcdf.nc'.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</para><code>import arcpy

# Check out the ArcGIS Spatial Analyst extension license
arcpy.CheckOutExtension("Spatial")
# Import custom toolbox
arcpy.ImportToolbox("c:/tools/Multidimension Supplemental Tools.pyt")

# Set local variables
in_zone_data = "c:/data/zones.tif"
in_value_file = "c:/data/netcdf.nc"
variable = "temperature"
out_netcdf_file = "c:/data/zonal_netcdf.nc"
statistic_type = "MEAN"

# Execute Multidimensional Zonal Statistics
arcpy.MultidimensionalZonalStatistics_mds(in_zone_data, in_value_file, \
    variable, out_netcdf_file, statistic_type, "IGNORE", "Value")</code></scriptExample></scriptExamples></tool><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv></metadata>
